hello everyone in this video i'm going
to discuss bearing and serving and also
different systems of bearing will be
discussed
bearing is just another name of angular
serving but that angle is to be bigger
from some reference line and the
difference line is usually the north
line or the south line there are
different systems of bearing like one
system is a whole circle bearing system
and another is the ordinal bearing
system that is also called reduced
bearing system now let's discuss whole
circle bearing system we know the
standard directions in whole circle
bearing system the angle is always being
measured from north reference line the
one which is being represented with red
line and in whole circle bearing system
the angle is always being bigger
clockwise since the angle is always
being measured from north and it is
always being make it clockwise therefore
the range of that angle will always be
from 0 to 360 degree now as far as the
representation of a bearing of a line is
concerned the bearing of the line in a
whole circle bearing system is
represented as
for example if that line lies in the
northeast quadrant the angle should be
from 0 to 90 degree let's say that the
line lies here and that angle makes it
is 50 degrees so representation is just
the degree symbol along with the angle
similarly if the line lies in southeast
quadrant then the angle would be from 90
to 180 degree let's say that the line is
over here then the angle would be let's
say 120 degree and if that angle exceeds
180 degree then the quadrant would be
southwest quadrant and in that quadrant
the angle will vary from 180 to 270
degree and let's say that the line is
over here and that line makes an angle
of 200 degree and if the bearing of the
line xc 270 degree then the line will
lie in northwest quadrant and in that
quadrant the range is from 270 degree to
360 degree let's say that the line is
lying here
and the angle that it makes with the
north clockwise is 300 degree now this
is all from whole circle bearing system
now let's discuss about the quadrantal
bearing system
the same reference lines in quadrantal
bearing system the angle can be measured
from north or south whichever is near so
angle can be measured from north angle
can also be measured from south
depending upon the location of the line
if the line is nearer to south then the
angle would be measured from north and
if the line is nearer to south then
angle would be measured from south and
angle and quarter bearing system the
angle can be measured clockwise or
counterclockwise like clockwise from
north clockwise from south
anti-clockwise from north are
anti-clockwise from south and if this is
so then angle will always range from 0
to 90 degree if the angle is to be
measured from
north to east the angle would be from 0
to 90 if that line
exceeds the 90 degree then that line
would be in southeast quadrant then
south would be nearer through that line
and then bearing would be measured from
south
if we are on northwest quadrant the
angle would be always 0 to 90 and same
is the case if we are in southwest
quadrant now as far as the
representation of the bearing and
quadrant bearing system is concerned the
angle is being represented with the
quadrant in which that particular line
is lying for example if that line is
lined in northeast quadrant so n e
should be written along with the angle
similarly if the line lies in southeast
quadrant then along with the angle s e
should be written and if the line lies
in south west quadrant then along with
the angle southwest is to build in same
is the case when the line lies in
northwest quadrant the nw is to be
written along with that angle so this is
all from the introduction to the bearing
and introduction to the different
systems of bearing in next coming videos
i will be discussing about the
interconversion of different system of
bearing like how we can convert one
system of bearing to another system of
bearing if the angle is given in
quadrantal bearing system then how you
can convert into full circle bearing
system and vice versa is also to be
discussed in next coming videos thank
you for watching this video